The title makes it seem like I'm going
to be selling you some powder in this
video. The Physionic Liver Cleanser
9000. I'll go ahead and tell you that I
am not. I'll tell you everything that
you need to know and it's extremely
simple. But really, that's the most
boring part because what I'm excited to
show you is the relationship between
BCAAs, the same branched chain amino
acids found in many proteins, and liver
disease, and how this powder cleanses
the liver, the colon, and your blood in
such a way that it fixes said liver
disease. The powder is
resistant starch and I'll tell you how I
use it every day that I can. Across
multiple scientific reviews, it's
described that the higher your blood
BCAA levels, that's those branch chain
amino acids like leucine, veene, and
isolucine, the greater your risk of
NAFLD
of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. So,
you may not realize it, but I've already
set the stage two problematic points.
the blood and the liver. Now, we'll be
adding your intestines, your colon
specifically to the mix soon. In fact,
this relationship between BCAAs and
liver disease can be seen here. The
vertical axis is liver fat and the
horizontal is blood BCAAs. We see a
relationship with increased BCAAs
associate with more liver fat, a bad
thing. Now, of course, this is an
association and these associations are
found across the literature. Now, the
question may have popped into your head,
well, if uh high blood BCAAs are related
to liver disease, should I stop
consuming BCAAs? Well, not quite. In
fact, that question is something I'll
probably end up covering in more depth
in the future. But for now, the research
indicates that this relationship is not
primarily driven by consuming BCAAs,
though it is a source of blood BCAAs,
but rather a mixture of three things.
consumption, production, and impaired
clearance. Now, consumption is obvious,
but the other two are a bit more
nebulous. The impaired clearance means
that the cells of the body aren't able
to take up BCAAs out of the blood and
use them or catabolize, break them down.
This implies some form of pre-existing
problem in metabolism, usually major
problems like being overfat, insulin
resistant, and more. The takeaway here
isn't that BCAAs are on their own
problematic, but that they can be a
problem or a signal of a problem if the
body is metabolically compromised, like
an insulin resistant state or generally
being overweight. Still, that leaves one
critical prong of the trident,
production. Your body can also produce
BCAAs, and in this case, we don't want
it to, which we'll get into in just a
minute. The production side is where
resistant starch powder can have a
massive impact because BCAAs are
produced by particular bacteria in our
gut. And here enters our third
anatomical musketeer, the colon. Inside
your colon are billions of microbes
including bacteria. And some of those
bacteria produce these BCAAs which is
associated with a disregulated
microbiome in people with fatty liver
disease. We can see such a relationship
here. The more the red squares that you
see, the more the positive correlation,
meaning more of that molecule is
produced. The molecules are listed at
the bottom and IHC is liver fat. The
right side is a bunch of groupings of
microbial gene pathways. And we're
zooming in to look at four of these gene
pathways. All of them are tied to BCAA
production. And at the very bottom you
see some of the microbes, the bacteria
responsible for these gene pathways. So
to simplify, we see a bunch of red above
IHTC, that's liver fat, indicating more
is present. And when we zoom into some
of these gene pathways linked to BCAA
production, we see the relationship
between more liver fat and BCAA
production gene pathways. Of course,
this is still association, but we can
even test this through experimentation
by simply taking one of these BCAAs,
veiling, and applying it to liver cells
seen here. This is the amount of
triglyceride or fat molecules stored in
the liver cells with veene exposure at
increasing concentrations or without
veiling. If the bars go up, that
directly implicates veiling as
stimulating fat storage in the liver
cells. And clearly that's the case
though there only needs to be a minimum
threshold reached as there's no dose
response as in more veiling more fat
storage. As a note these liver cells
were cancerous liver cells. So these may
not be reproducible in normal liver
cells. It speaks again more to the
necessary underlying dysfunction before
BCAAs enact a harmful role. All right
your eyes might be a bit uh crosseyed.
So, let me pull us out of the data muk
and simplify this. The main point here
is that our gut microbiome produces
BCAAs which add to blood BCAA levels
which directly increases the storage of
fat in our liver causing fatty liver
disease. Now, we have our three sites,
the colon, the blood, and the liver. How
do resistant starches cleanse or in a
less woo woo language improve all three?
And how much should we be using to get
these benefits? Well, check it out.
We're looking at colonic production of
all three BCAAs. The CS condition there
is the nonresistant starch control
condition. And the right is the
resistant starch condition. One thing to
note is that this experiment was taking
human microbiome samples and implanting
them into mice. A bit of a hybrid
experiment. Notice how the resistant
starch supplemented human samples led to
significant reductions in colonic BCAA
production. Then when we look at the
strict human data after months of
supplementing with resistant starches in
blue, we see reductions in blood branch
chain amino acids indicated as the blue
bars move in the opposite direction of
the red control group. And in the
negative Zcore direction we see that
universally veiling leucine and
isolucine are reduced in the blood.
Okay, that's two cleansed. Now on to the
most important one, the liver. The liver
data is pretty revealing, but there's
also data on toxin levels in the blood
and how some people are higher
responders than others and other
metabolic effects of resistant starches.
I'm covering that in the extended
analysis of the one that you're
currently watching. Now, if you're
interested, it's an extended video comes
with an article, a summary of the main
points, and that's just one of the perks
that you'll get as a physionic insider,
which includes all of these perks as
well. For example, where can you get
reputable resistance starches? I have a
master supplement guide that tells you
some good sources, and there's much more
to the insiders, but I'll leave it
there. If you're interested in access to
all my work, hop aboard the Physionic
Insiders. Join using the link in the
description. For this, we can lean on
the human data and measures of IHTC.
Remember that one? That's the liver fat.
Now, after 4 months of supplementation,
those using resistant starches
experienced a notable reduction, maybe
what, like 25%. What do you think in
intrahippatic fat or liver fat? So the
point here being across all three
categories, production by microbiome,
blood BCAAs and liver fat burden,
resistant starch consumption has
widpread benefit. So yes, the stuff
works and it works very well. Anyway,
enough science. Hopefully I've convinced
you that resistant starches have some
pretty great benefits. Though the focus
here has been on the microbiome, BCAA,
liver fat relationship. There's
certainly other ways that resistant
starches help us. I usually consume
about 40 grams of resistant starch in
some form of shake. Now, I usually
switch it up and it doesn't really
matter that much so long as it's
somewhat appetizing. If you have
recipes, I'm all ears. Generally, you
can get resistant starches from sources
like green banana powder, high amalos
maze, and potato starch. Here's the
kicker, though. Like I said, there's
other ways that resistant starches help
our body with impressive results, but
some people get less benefit than
others, and I cover that in my next
video. Check it out right here. Hope you
found this as fascinating as I did.
Thanks for tuning in, and I'll catch you
in the next one. See you.